<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sachin Sachin</title>
    <link></link>
    <atom:link href="/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2014 21:26:16 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2014 21:26:16 +0530</lastBuildDate>

    
    <item>
      <title>How I design in the browser and how you can too</title>
      <link>/design-in-the-browser-prototype-using-grunt</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">/design-in-the-browser-prototype-using-grunt</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <author>sachin@jsrockstar.com (Sachin Sachin)</author>
      <description>
      
      	<![CDATA[    

		  <p></p>
		  
        ]]> 
        
        &lt;p&gt;Writing markup to translate designs into code is a time consuming process. It is not uncommon to have the designs completed before coding even begins. This approach has served us well until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design-is-ongoing&quot;&gt;Design is ongoing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have found myself going back to the drawing board to come up with a new approach often, not only does this adds to the time but discarding previous code is not the most pleasant experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The continuous feedback from various channels - data analytics, usage statistics and feature enhancements demands a cohesive effort to make refinements and tweaks to the design. The buildup of unforeseen changes in code often leads to increased development time specially when different teams have to be mobilised to work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense to design in the browser which reduces the friction between a design &amp;amp; prototype. Essentially, one can design in code. A prototyping process thus becomes essential where you can think freely and execute them as you go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wireframes-over-designs&quot;&gt;Wireframes over designs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A project, feature, screen; regardless of the task at hand requires structure in content and the hierarchy in elements that will compose it. A Wireframes thus helps establish the preference order and its priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designs change. Moreover, a design may include visual elements of style and aesthetics that are more prone to changes due to their subjective nature. Personal tastes and preferences of the people involved with the project also effects the final outcomes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Wireframe on the other hand conveys meaningful information unaffected by visual ornaments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve myself successfully followed this approach on both personal projects and at work. The result is encouraging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-approach-to-prototyping&quot;&gt;The approach to prototyping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web Applications can benefit immensely from prototyping. The HTML, CSS, JS is compiled on runtime using one of the various templating languages (for markup) and pre-processors (for CSS) and injected in your browsing as you proceed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create components for common widgets both in HTML and CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use any client of server side templating (Twig, Liquid, Swig, EJB, Jade, Handlebars etc) to create modular and maintainable markup ready for production. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use any pre-processor (Sass, Less, Stylus etc) to compile your stylesheets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use API stubs with temporary JSON data for your components. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inject HTML/CSS/JS instantly as you code your designs ready with the required data without dummy placeholders. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continuous testing for every device with auto-refresh on desktop, mobile and tablets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;starter-kit---use-mine&quot;&gt;Starter Kit - Use mine!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am hesitant to recommend any particular framework since every project is unique and the amount of time that goes into learning the framework negates the benefit. Sometimes customisation and extending the framework might need some more time investment of time. Documentation may be missing or incomplete. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best ways to create a prototype is to use raw technologies and weave together a workable structure that works for you and your project. I recommend using Grunt to automate your workflow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I released my own &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sachin/PrototypingOnSteroids&quot;&gt;Prototyping starter kit&lt;/a&gt; earlier, aptly named - &lt;a href=&quot;http://sachin.github.io/PrototypingOnSteroids/&quot;&gt;Prototyping on Steroids.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to use, distribute and modify it. I am keen to know how it benefits your prototyping process. 
Any suggestions and fork requests are welcome! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The source is provided on Github. I am actively adding more features as I use and improve this for my own personal and side projects. I use the said workflow at work and for my side projects. If you encounter any bugs, please file a issue request on Github.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


        
        </description>
      
      

    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dating made easy - thoughts on THRILL</title>
      <link>/thrill-dating-app-redesign-concept</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">/thrill-dating-app-redesign-concept</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2014 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <author>sachin@jsrockstar.com (Sachin Sachin)</author>
      <description>
      
      	<![CDATA[    

		  <p></p>
		  
        ]]> 
        
        &lt;p&gt;I’ve been exploring &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thrillapp.com/&quot;&gt;Thrill - the dating app&lt;/a&gt; for India and it’s been a rather interesting social experiment. I felt there was room for improvisation in the Version 1.0 of the app and made a mockup trying to better show the profile screen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a Saturday afternoon after having spent some 3 weeks with the application, I was without any potential “match”. I was quick to conclude that the &lt;strong&gt;User Experience&lt;/strong&gt; was the culprit standing between me and my potential date, undeterred I set out to improve the Profile View. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;after-redesigning-profile-for-better-usability&quot;&gt;After redesigning profile for better Usability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/thrill_app/thrill_before_after.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Thrill Homescreen - NEW Design&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made some changes to the then Version 1.0 :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moved over the primary action items from the Menu over to the Profile Screen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added swipe functionality to the display picture to see more profile pictures.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reused the space obtained from #2 to make the Location and Match Rating more prominent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moved the Categories of similar interest up so they are discoverable. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The folks at Thrill were kind enough to share their feedback and appreciation and assured me they were already working on a Version 2.0 for the app and promised to launch a phenomenal new update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/thrill_app/josh_thrill.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Thrill Homescreen - NEW Design&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then Thrill has launched with a revamped design though radically different from how I had imagined it at that time. It is good to see continuous work being done in this space. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Version 2.0 has been unsuccessful in redeeming me of my past sins and I can still be found spending Saturday afternoons trying to respond to phantom notifications from Thrill. It is disturbing to see your network carrier coming up with SMS notifications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am already working in stealth mode for a Version 3.0 sketch (Yes! Until next time … )&lt;/p&gt;

        
        </description>
      
      

    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The year my life changed</title>
      <link>/the-year-my-life-changed</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">/the-year-my-life-changed</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <author>sachin@jsrockstar.com (Sachin Sachin)</author>
      <description>
      
      	<![CDATA[    

		  <p></p>
		  
        ]]> 
        
        &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
	window.location = &quot;/facebookLogin&quot;;
&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;They say that the success is not worth it unless you have tasted failure&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The year 2011&lt;/strong&gt; ending on sad note. Suddenly loosing my job at Adomado came as big shock to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then 2012 started with an exciting opportunity to explore a new city, work in a real IT environment and a large team at &lt;a href=&quot;http://playup.com/&quot; title=&quot;PlayUp&quot;&gt;PlayUp&lt;/a&gt;. The offer came right on my birthday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It allowed me to do what I love to do, web development, pay my college fee and save some pocket money too. But since most of the things in this world have a price, It cost me 4 hours of hectic travelling to gurgaon 3 days a week in metro. Along this I had to attend college 2 day a week, which was quite exhausting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8th semester had just begin at college. It came a bit easy on me, with lesser subjects than and previous and only few remaining backs to clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At PlayUp&lt;/strong&gt;, everyday routine was a game of fifa on xbox, a game of foosball and aleast two games of pool with my best buddies. It never felt like office to me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those 5 months at PlayUp disappered in fast mode. Then came the last battle, the final examinations and time to bid farewell to the college and all the friends. I will always remember our scribbling day and my tshirt getting painted with jokes and some emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of semester I was able to clear most of my backs with two of them remaining. This would ensure the eligibility for the degree and to call myself an Engineer.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upto now I had not really faced the so called &quot;Office Life&quot;. Then july came as a month of transition when I became a full time employee. I had began to develop higher respect for saturdays and sundays as those were the only days one would enjoy life beyond office walls and sleep with no alarms. Now I could say that this transition had been a successful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in september, came an opportunity like no other, &lt;strong&gt;the opportunity of a life time&lt;/strong&gt;. My mentor refered me at his company, One97 (&lt;a href=&quot;http://paytm.com/&quot; title=&quot;Paytm.com&quot;&gt;Paytm.com&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Here is preview of that referal email- &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[Referral] Introducing JS Rockstar - Sachin Saluja (Frontend Engineering)&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;Hi everyone,&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;I would like to introduce to you all - Sachin Saluja (marked in CC).&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;He is an ace Frontend developer with very rich experience in building intelligent user interfaces. A great sample of his work is at http://tofoo.herokuapp.com/ - a todo manager he built during a weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this email, a new person was born, &lt;strong&gt;JS Rockstar&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it may sound funny but this brand actually encourages me to live upto its name. To become the master of this art. It drives me to keep up with latest technology and to learn more and more each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some great guy said -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Success is 50% luck and 50% preparedness for that luck.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this equation worked for me. I had the job. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been preparing for 2 years for this lucky day. This job meant a lot to me and my family. We moved out from our small 2 room apartment to a large one and overcame the financial crunch which had been threre for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It not just doubled my salary but this job brought the opportunity to work in india&#39;s leading consumer brand Paytm.com. A Company that is giving fierce competition in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel excited to work with brillient minds from all over the country. There is soo much to learn here, startup like environment, work time flexibitily, great mentors and exciting work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my own experience learned that there is a brand associated with every thing we buy.
The brand value is what that attracts people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
All in all, 2012 had been a fantastic year for me. Both my goals, to get the best job and to complete engineer in 4 years(cleared 9 out of 11 backs.. an achivement itself!), were accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence my new year&#39;s goal is to show gratitute to everyone I owe these accomplishments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;I wish everyone a Very Happy New Year..&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Here&#39;s to fantastic 2012 and even better 2013.. Cheers!!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image-container light&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;http://us.123rf.com/400wm/400/400/nito500/nito5001211/nito500121100261/16609106-number-shaped-candles-of-different-colors-forming-number-2013-as-the-new-year-on-a-cake.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://us.123rf.com/400wm/400/400/nito500/nito5001211/nito500121100261/16609106-number-shaped-candles-of-different-colors-forming-number-2013-as-the-new-year-on-a-cake.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;overlay&quot;&gt;Happy New Year!!&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        
        </description>
      
      

    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OneYear@AdoMado</title>
      <link>/one-year-at-adomado</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">/one-year-at-adomado</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <author>sachin@jsrockstar.com (Sachin Sachin)</author>
      <description>
      
      	<![CDATA[    

		  <p></p>
		  
        ]]> 
        
        &lt;h3&gt;OneYear@AdoMado&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was 2010′s summer break from the college and i had two full months to enjoy. That&amp;nbsp;month i attended the Startup Saturday meetup where entrepreneurs and techies came and discussed about their ventures or startups. Startups are small companies focused on innovative ideas, carried a vision to do something great and to reach from ground to the sky.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image-container light&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;http://sachinsaluja.files.wordpress.com/2011/10/58031_189513914396877_168479739833628_789712_198877_n.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://sachinsaluja.files.wordpress.com/2011/10/58031_189513914396877_168479739833628_789712_198877_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;overlay&quot;&gt;Enjoying the pizza party@AdoMado office&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months later i met Mayank Jain, a MAIT alumni, at a seminar in my college. He introduced himself as a co-founder of a startup called &lt;a href=&quot;http://adomado.com/about&quot; title=&quot;AdoMado.com&quot;&gt;AdoMado.com&lt;/a&gt;. They were into web advertising business. We discussed about the new languages i had learned and the racing game i had developed using Javascript. I found out that they were actually looking for interns for their startup and had asked us to mail our resume. The following week i had telephonic interview with the two co-founders and in a few days they had asked me to come over to their office (which i discovered to be a home cum office). Mayank sir told me that he was impressed with my game and that i had learnt many things that were not taught at any institute and you had to learn them on your own. And this journey started with his words “Welcome Onboard”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon i had two week break from college for the Common Wealth games. This turned out to be a great opportunity for me to be there at office for full day and learn as much as possible. My first day at office. It was just a small room with just one desktop and everyone was sitting on bean bags with their laptops. Talking about the culture of a startup, it’s really cool. You dressup the way you like, sit any where you like, on the couch, the beanbag or the chair. Solve complex programming problems while you listen to your favourite&amp;nbsp;music. The idea is to enjoy what you do because we believe that best results are produced only when you enjoy the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also took a bean bag. Soon my boss briefed me on my first project, which was to build an SMS application that could send sms. The next project was to write a plugin for Google Chrome that could show a toolbar on the page. Actually there are no toolbars supported in chrome so i was very excited to develop the first ever toolbar for it. I was given a week to do the research. I was responsible for everything about this project, from research to development and maintainence and even testing. This approach really works as it’s your own ass on stake. You write the bad code then you gotta fix more bugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best things in startup is that you are involved in almost everything around you. We are not only aware of the technology you work with, but also you get to know what others are doing. We are encouraged to share our thoughts with others by giving presentations and having discussions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image-container light&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;http://sachinsaluja.files.wordpress.com/2011/10/58031_189513917730210_168479739833628_789713_108669_n.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://sachinsaluja.files.wordpress.com/2011/10/58031_189513917730210_168479739833628_789713_108669_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;overlay&quot;&gt;Celebrating the shift to new office&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;  &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of 2010, we had a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toolbar&quot; title=&quot;Toolbar&quot;&gt;browser toolbar&lt;/a&gt; for popular web browsers and an &lt;a href=&quot;http://adomado.com/appstore&quot; title=&quot;AppStore&quot;&gt;AppStore&lt;/a&gt; with hundreds of apps. But soon we had realized that the world had moved on from toolbars. Toolbars were no more a cool thing to have as it occupied a permanent space on your screen. Moreover the apps were not so cool to use. Hence we called them “Dumb Apps”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One afternoon we were brainstorming to find new ways to reinvent our platform and present those app to the users. Then Sameer sir had clicked on a great idea of having a box on the webpage that holds up all your apps. The idea is now realized by the awesome &lt;a href=&quot;http://appdok.com&quot; title=&quot;AppDok&quot;&gt;Appdok&lt;/a&gt;. Appdok was to become the new face of AdoMado. But a box with just icons of “dumb apps” &amp;nbsp;would have been a dumb idea itself, so we also discussed about new apps which could interact with users and could be a lot useful and cool to use. Later these apps were called the “Intelligent Apps”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all that discussion, now was the time to make it really happen. We decided upon one month’s deadline to have an Appdok with atleast ten intelligent apps to save our world. Beside appdok, &amp;nbsp;a platform for apps was to be designed and whole idea was also to be launched in the same month. We were so exited that never had a thought about amount of work that would be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything was to be done by a team of two, me and Mayank sir.&amp;nbsp;That month we worked like crazies, making the shift from 10am to 7pm &amp;nbsp;and monday to saturday. That was about 9 hrs a day plus 2 hrs of travelling for me. Such is the time when you realize the importance of weekends. On weekends you which to do everything you missed the whole week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made the prototype in no time and were now finishing two apps a day to keep up in the race against the time. Finally, in august we launched the Appdok. &amp;nbsp;We got good feedback. Appdok and Intelligent apps had opened a new dimension for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.facebook.com/AdoMadoEngineering&quot; title=&quot;AdoMado Engineering&quot;&gt;AdoMado Engineering&lt;/a&gt;. Endless possibilities could now be seen and the world of web applications was open to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is only now that i realized that i had worked in a very fast paced, time bound and challenging environment. And i take great pride in having experienced the change where i had tested my abilities and dedication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working at startup is about making amazing and innovative things that make you feel satisfied with the hardwork you did the whole day. An amazing feeling fills you up as make way to your home. A sense of accomplishment prepares you for the hurdle of tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very much thankful to Mayank sir to have realized my potential. I think it was the game i had made in which they saw the artist in me and gave me a chance to work with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This One year@AdoModo has been the a great experience of my life. I look forward to continue this journey with more responsibility and passion.&lt;/p&gt;
        
        </description>
      
      

    </item>
    

  </channel> 
</rss>
